{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "An attempt to dissolve this alliance ended at Rotebro when king Hans captured the peasant leader Sten Sture the Elder. This alliance was weakened when the Engelbrekt Rebellion managed to unseat Erik of Pomerania in favor of Christopher of Bavaria. The 1523 coronation of Gustav I Vasa marked the end of this alliance, which was constructed by Margaret I and Haakon VII in order to challenge the Hanseatic League. For ten points, name this medieval union of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden.",
      "answer": "Kalmar Union or the Union of Kalmaris"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer depicted Pontus de la Gardie’s march on Kaksialmi in one work. His seventh and final symphony is a one-movement work in C major. This composer of the Karelia Suite wrote a piece often performed under titles like “Impromptu” or “Scandinavian Choral March” due to its forbidden nationalist sentiment. This composer adapted stories from his national epic, the Kalevala, in works such as the Lemminkainen Suite. For ten points, name this composer of Finlandia.",
      "answer": "Jean Sibelius"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was preceded by a rally at Blue Island, where anything that could be lit on fire was. Richard Olney helped mitigate this event by obtaining an injunction barring labor leaders from joining it. Though Illinois governor John Peter Altgeld declined to intervene in it, Grover Cleveland sent Nelson Miles’ troops to break it up because it was disrupting federal mail. Eugene Debs was arrested for his role in, for ten points, what 1894 worker’s strike targeting a sleeping car manufacturer?",
      "answer": "Pullman strike"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s skyline features two cranes, known as “Samson and Goliath,” in the shipyards of Harland and Wolff. Its neighborhoods of Short Strand and Cluan Place are separated by a “peace line,” as are Falls Road and Shankill Road. The RMS Titanic was built in this city, which was home to a parliament at Stormont which was dissolved during the height of the Troubles. The Good Friday Agreement was signed in, for ten points, what city, the capital of Northern Ireland?",
      "answer": "Belfast"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader survived a failed coup attempt, the February 26 Incident, which ended the period of “government by assassination.” The first time many of this ruler’s subjects heard his voice was during the Jewel Voice Broadcast. After defeat at the Battle of Saipan, this man ordered his subjects to commit suicide rather than be captured. Douglas MacArthur allowed this man to keep his position during the American post-war occupation. For ten points, name this emperor of Japan during World War II.",
      "answer": "Emperor Hirohito or the Showa Emperor"
    },
    {
      "question": "An amendment co-sponsored by this Senator and Mark Hatfield brought the chamber to a halt when this man accused each senator of sending 50,000 Americans to their premature deaths. This man co-chaired a commission with Donald Fraser that led to a surge in the amount and importance of presidential primaries. This man lost an election to an incumbent who promised “peace with honor” and claimed this man would settle for “peace at any price.” For ten points, name this anti-war South Dakotan Democrat who lost every state but Massachusetts to Richard Nixon in 1972.",
      "answer": "George McGovern"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. In one work, one individual with this role has to be replaced by Polus and then Callicles, all of whom argue that rhetoric is superior to philosophy. In another work, a person who performs this role gives a hypothetical argument about justice’s origins as a means to an end. That individual, Glaucon, takes on this role after Thrasymachus, another of these people, fails to convince a man that justice is the “interest of the stronger.” For ten points, identify this role, in which people served as sounding boards for a certain ancient Athenian philosopher.",
      "answer": [
        "interlocutors of Socrates",
        "descriptive answers such as “people who talk to or argue with, etc. Socrates”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An unsuccessful 1970 fascist coup in this country was instigated by a man nicknamed “The Black Prince.” This country’s communist party forged a mainstream alliance in the Historic Compromise. Antonio Negri was arrested, then released, for leading the Red Brigades, who kidnapped and killed a prime minister of this country during its turbulent Years of Lead. For ten points, name this European country that chose to become a republic in 1946 and was led by Aldo Moro.",
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1755, this city was struck by the Cape Ann earthquake, the largest earthquake to hit the northeastern United States. This city’s namesake “Fruit Company” was a predecessor of the United Fruit Company in the 19th century. This city’s cultural elite were known as “Brahmins” and included the Lowell and Cabot families. John Adams gained fame for defending British soldiers accused of participating in a 1775 “Massacre” in, for ten points, what capital city of Massachusetts?",
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Raiders came back to defeat this team in the 1968 “Heidi” Game, whose ending was cut off on television by a children’s movie. This team won its only Super Bowl by a score of 16 to 7 against Earl Morrall and Johnny Unitas after the quarterback guaranteed an upset victory. Joe Namath is the all-time leading passer for this team, the winner of Super Bowl 3 over the Baltimore Colts. For ten points, name this NFL team that shares the Meadowlands of New Jersey with the New York Giants.",
      "answer": "New York Jets"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was targeted by the Aberdeen Act, which authorized the Royal Navy to board its ships. A period of regency in this country led to a series of independence revolts, such as the Ragamuffin War. During the Peninsular War, Prince Regent Joao moved his monarchy to this country. It fought the Platine War against Argentina and was part of the Triple Alliance that defeated Paraguay. For ten points, name this country that gained its independence from Portugal after the Treaty of Rio de Janeiro.",
        "answer": "Empire of Brazil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brazil abolished slavery with the passage of this 1888 law, thus becoming the last Western country to do so.",
        "answer": "Golden Law or Lei A´urea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Second Manifesto represented a shift away from this practice, which was ruled illegal in the case of Reynolds v. United States. Wilford Woodruff issued an 1890 declaration against this practice. In 2008, the YFZ Ranch in Texas was raided for practicing this tradition as part of a fundamentalist version of the Mormon faith, which turned away from this practice despite Joseph Smith and Brigham Young’s acceptance of it. For ten points, name this marital practice of taking more than one spouse.",
        "answer": [
          "polygamy",
          "descriptions before “taking more” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During oral arguments in this 2015 Supreme Court case, Justices Alito, Scalia, and Roberts all made comments claiming that this decision could be used to justify plural marriages. This decision did overturn Baker v. Nelson.",
        "answer": "Obergefell v. Hodges"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the site of the 1909 Goudi coup, which forced its King George I to bring in a reformist prime minister. The London Conference of 1832 established this country and made the Bavarian prince Otto its king. This country and Serbia fought Bulgaria over the occupation of Macedonia in the Second Balkan War. Andreas and Georgios Papandreou served as Prime Minister of, for ten points, what country that, in 1896, hosted the first modern Summer Olympics in Athens?",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was born as a prince of Greece and Denmark. He is now the royal consort of another country, having served in its Royal Navy during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh",
          "either portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One novel by this author sets scenes at a tavern named The Boot, which was used by the participants in the Gordon Riots. Another novel by this author is partially set at Satis House, inspired by a mansion of the same name in Kent, where the widow Miss Havisham lives; in that novel, a convict who is sent to Australia makes a fortune and becomes the benefactor of Pip. For ten points, name this British author of serial novels like Barnaby Rudge and Great Expectations.",
        "answer": "Charles Dickens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Dickens’s Sketches by Boz involves a visit to what notorious London prison, the birthplace of DeFoe’s Moll Flanders and temporary residence of Ben Jonson after his duel with Gabriel Spenser?",
        "answer": "Newgate Prison"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event in 2015, 107 people were killed by a crane collapse, while a stampede in 1990 killed over 1,400 participants. This event commemorates the seeking of water by Hajar, who ran between the hills of Safa and Marwah seven times; that path is now enclosed by the Masjid al-Haram. Other rituals that take place during this annual event include tawaf, in which one walks around the Kaaba. For ten points, name this pillar of Islam, requiring an annual pilgrimage to Mecca.",
        "answer": "hajj"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The water sought by Hagar and drunk by pilgrims on hajj comes from this well, within the Masjid al-Haram.",
        "answer": "Zamzam Well"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At one point, this man’s base of power was the North American city of New Castle. This man was imprisoned in the Tower of London for writing the tract The Sandy Foundation Shaken, and, while in jail, he further angered his captors by penning the anti-monarchist No Cross, No Crown. He incorporated principles of his faith into a Frame of Government for a colony he founded. For ten points, name this Quaker who oversaw the planning of Philadelphia in a state that now bears his name.",
        "answer": "William Penn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "William Penn’s charter to Pennsylvania brought him into legal conflict with Charles, a member of this English family which held the title of Baron Baltimore. George, this family’s patriarch, received the original charter for Maryland.",
        "answer": [
          "Calvert family",
          "Charles and/or George Calvert"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Projects along this river include the Elephant Butte and Amistad Dams. The mouth of this river was once home to the port of Bagdad, which was heavily used by the Confederacy. A swing bridge spanning this river connects the cities of Matomoros and Brownsville, and it was claimed as the southern border of a republic that gained its independence after the Battle of San Jacinto. For ten points, name this river that serves as the boundary between Mexico and the State of Texas.",
        "answer": "Rio Grande"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Texas Revolution, Mexico claimed that this other river, not the Rio Grande, was the southern border of Texas.",
        "answer": "Nueces River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Leo Amery attacked this man in Parliament by quoting Cromwell’s “In the name of God, go!” speech. This man was forced to resign after the failure of the expedition to Norway. He declared that there would be “peace in our time” after signing the Munich Agreement, part of his policy of appeasement towards Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this British prime minister who was succeeded by Winston Churchill at the beginning of World War II.",
        "answer": "Neville Chamberlain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chamberlain served in this position under his predecessor, Stanley Baldwin. Holders of this position in the United Kingdom manage the Treasury.",
        "answer": "Chancellor of the Exchequer"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Bill of Rights",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Number of amendments included in the U.S. Bill of Rights.",
          "answer": "10"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that protects freedom of speech and religion.",
          "answer": "1st Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that protects against “cruel and unusual punishments.”",
          "answer": "8th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that demands “just compensation” when private property is taken for public use.",
          "answer": "5th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the Bill of Rights and owner of a plantation at Montpelier.",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "People for whom pay raises are restricted by the 27th Amendment, an idea originally proposed with the Bill of Rights.",
          "answer": [
            "members of Congress",
            "Representatives and/or Senators and any equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Process by which a court uses the 14th Amendment to apply the Bill of Rights to the states.",
          "answer": [
            "selective and/or total incorporation",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1833 Supreme Court case against the city of Baltimore that explicitly banned that process.",
          "answer": "Barron v. Baltimore"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Spanish Armada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the Armada was launched.",
          "answer": [
            "1500s",
            "16th century",
            "1588"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Spain who launched the Armada.",
          "answer": "Philip II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Queen whose Tilbury Speech rallied the waiting English army.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth I"
        },
        {
          "question": "North Atlantic water current that pushed the defeated, escaping Armada into the coasts of Scotland and Ireland.",
          "answer": "Gulf Stream"
        },
        {
          "question": "French port city across the Channel from Dover where the Armada waited, in crescent formation, for Parma’s army to board.",
          "answer": "Calais"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of warship, including “hellburners,” which the English used to scatter that crescent formation.",
          "answer": [
            "fireship",
            "any description of a ship set on fire and/or used as a bomb"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish Duke who was commander-in-chief of the Armada.",
          "answer": [
            "Alonso P´erez de Guzm´an y de Zu´n˜iga-Sotomayor, Duke of Medina Sidonia",
            "any underlined part",
            "do not prompt if “Medina”",
            "“Sidonia” is given alone"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Flemish port town where an indecisive battle cost the Armada just five ships, but prevented it from picking up Parma’s army.",
          "answer": "Battle of Gravelines"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Sri Lanka",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European power that occupied it in 1640, ruling it in an extensive colonial empire from Amsterdam.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of the Seven United Netherlands or the Netherlands",
            "Dutch Republic",
            "Republic of the Seven United Provinces"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European power that discovered it and built a fort at Colombo. Its explorers included Vasco da Gama.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion followed by the majority of its residents, primarily the Theravada sect.",
          "answer": "Buddhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cash crop introduced in the 19th century by the British, produce into black and green drinks.",
          "answer": "tea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group on Sri Lanka that formed a Tiger resistance movement against the majority Sinhalese.",
          "answer": [
            "Tamil",
            "Tamil Tigers and other elaborations"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to the island while under colonial rule.",
          "answer": "Ceylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native kingdom that resisted European occupation until the British conquest. It began as an ally of the Kingdom of Kotte.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Kandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian dynasty that occupied Sri Lanka under Rajendra. They dominated the Indian Ocean stretching all the way to the Malay Peninsula.",
          "answer": "Chola dynasty"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to Ammianus Marcellinus’ account of this battle, Bacurius led the Scutarii, who fled like cowards after leading an early, unordered charge. That acccount also details how, after this battle, the losing commander fled to a (20 pts)",
        "cottage, where he was burned to death by enemies unaware he was hiding inside. This battle could have been avoided with an armistice proposed by (10 pts)",
        "Fritigern. For ten points, name this monumental 378 AD defeat of Emperor Valens, a Gothic victory that doomed the Eastern Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Adrianople or Hadrianopolis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alfred Kempe’s false proof of this statement was exposed in 1890 by Percy Heawood. When applied to toroidal graphs, this statement has an upper bound of 7. This theorem was proven by Kenneth (20 pts)",
        "Appel and Wolfgang Haken, who used the University of Illinois’ resources to study nearly 2,000 cases in which different maps may have violated it. The first widely-accepted “proof by (10 pts)",
        "computer” was for, for ten points, what mathematical theorem regarding the number of colors required to shade a map without adjacent regions sharing a color?"
      ],
      "answer": "four-color map theorem ”color” is not needed after said"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For one post, this man was selected over William Paterson as a replacement for Oliver Ellsworth. John Adams claimed that the “proudest act of my life” was gifting this man to the American people. This man (20 pts)",
        "changed a previous tradition of delivering opinions seriatim. In one decision, he argued that a writ of mandamus could not be issued because the Judiciary Act of (10 pts)",
        "1789 was unconstitutional, thus establishing the power of judicial review. For ten points, name this third Chief Justice of the Supreme Court the author of the opinion in Marbury v. Madison."
      ],
      "answer": "John Marshall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader faced a scandal after pushing for Westland Helicopters to integrate with Sikorsky company rather than the European Agusta firm. The NUM was organized by Michael (20 pts)",
        "Scargill against this leader, who had ordered the closing of 150 coal mines. This leader’s popularity was greatly damaged by the “Community Charge” poll tax and the abolition of free (10 pts)",
        "dairy for school children, prompting her to be known as the “Milk Snatcher.” For ten points, name this Conservative Prime Minister of Britain known as the Iron Lady."
      ],
      "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A painting of an “interior” in this U.S. state shows the back of a woman sewing, as possibly seen through a window; that Edward Hopper painting can be viewed in this state at the Whitney Museum. The Oxbow was painted by (20 pts)",
        "Thomas Cole, a member of an artistic movement named for a natural feature in this state. John Trumbull painted The Surrender of General (10 pts)",
        "Burgoyne after the Battle of Saratoga in, for ten points, what state, the home of the Hudson River School and the Museum of Modern Art in Manhattan?"
      ],
      "answer": "New York"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, after Paul Tsongas won the New Hampshire primary, the second-place finisher declared himself “the Comeback Kid” and went on to win his party’s nomination. Another candidate in this year briefly (20 pts)",
        "dropped out of the race, apparently because Republicans had tried to ruin his daughter’s wedding; that candidate warned against the “giant sucking sound” of jobs going south to Mexico should his independent candidacy lose and (10 pts)",
        "NAFTA be passed. Ross Perot’s first presidential campaign took third in, for ten points, what election year in which Bill Clinton defeated incumbent George H. W. Bush?"
      ],
      "answer": "Presidential election of 1992"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man fought off Slavs threatening his Billung March and was forced to confront a rebellion of nobles by led by his son Liudolf. In order for this man to marry his wife Adelaide, she had to escape imprisonment by (20 pts)",
        "Berengar II, whom this man later defeated to become King of the Lombards. This ruler stopped the Magyar raids by winning the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lechfeld, leading to the creation of Hungary. Pope John XII crowned, for ten points, what German king who unified Germany and Italy into the Holy Roman Empire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Otto the Great or Otto I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader returned to power four years after a leaked speech revealed that the MSZP, his country’s Socialist Party, lied “morning, at noon, and at night” about its ability to govern. In 2014, this leader proposed “illberal democracy” and a governing style more like (20 pts)",
        "Turkey or Russia. 44% voter turnout stymied this Fidesz Party leader’s 2016 referendum opposing EU migrant quotas, a year after this leader built a barbed wire fence on his country’s southern border with (10 pts)",
        "Serbia. For ten points, name this current Prime Minister of Hungary."
      ],
      "answer": "Viktor Orban"
    }
  ]
}